An Inventory of the Conseil national de libération (Congo) Commandement des forces armées populaires Etat major général records
Hoover Institution Archives
Conseil national de libération (Congo) Commandement des forces armées populaires. Etat major général records
1959-1988
76079
Hoover Institution Archives
20 manuscript boxes, 1 reel of magnetic tape (6.1 linear feet)
Includes materials such as government records, correspondence, reports, orders, battle plans, and lists; all relating to military and political aspects of a rebellion in the Kwilu region of the Congo in 1964. Materials were collected and organized by Herbert F. Weiss, a scholar and professor of the City University of New York. Also includes indexes and summaries created by Weiss. A portion of the collection is also available on microfilm (21 reels). Sound use copy of sound recording available.
Conseil national de libération (Congo) Commandement des forces armées populaires. Etat major général.
Access
Microfilm use only. Use copies of sound recordings are available for immediate use.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1976.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Forms of Material Available
A portion of the collection is available on microfilm (21 reels)
Biography / Administrative History
The Kwilu Rebellion
The recently independent Belgian Congo (now Democratic Republic of Congo) experienced a wave of unrest in 1964, sparked by a rebellion in its Kwilu province under the leadership of Pierre Mulele. In the Kwilu province, a solid group of Mulele followers formed among members of his own ethnic group, the Mbunda, as well as among Antoine Gizenga's kinsmen, the Pende, both of whom had long been the target of government repression.
The Kwilu rebellion began in January 1964, when Mulelist insurgents attacked government outposts, mission stations, and company installations. Troops were immediately sent to the area, and by April a measure of stability had been restored to the area. However, the rebels did establish control over an entire region for a period of nearly two years, ending in December 1965. The initial success of Mulelism encouraged a series of further uprisings, which brought the central government to the brink of collapse.
Although the Kwilu rebellion was ultimately reduced by a combination of military force and regional economic stagnation and thus failed in its objective, it has attracted considerable scholarly attention because it illustrates the origination and evolution process of social movements in the postwar third world.
Additional Sources:
Hermann Kinder and Werner Hilgemann, The Anchor Atlas of World History, 2, Garden City, New York, 1978, p. 268.
Mark Traugott, "The Economic Origins of the Kwilu Rebellion," Comparative Studies in Society and History, Vol. 21, No. 3. (Jul., 1979), pp. 459-479.
Renee C. Fox, Willy de Craemer, and Jean-Marie Ribeaucourt "The Second Independence: A Case Study of the Kwilu Rebellion in the Congo (in Millennial Overtones in Rebellion)," Comparative Studies in Society and History, Vol. 8, No. 1. (Oct., 1965), pp. 78-109.
Scope and Content of Collection
Includes materials such as government records, correspondence, reports, orders, battle plans, and lists; all relating to military and political aspects of a rebellion in the Kwilu region of the Congo in 1964. Materials were collected and organized by Herbert F. Weiss, a scholar and professor of the City University of New York.
The Kwilu Rebellion documents were collected by Weiss after the materials were abandoned by a section of the Conseil national de libération (CNL) general headquarters unit near Gungu towards the end of 1964 or early 1965. A majority of the documents are dated in the spring and summer of 1964, the period of the highest amount of rebel activity. Documents created by the rebellion were individually numbered when filed and originally kept bound into rolls with bits of flexible root. Some papers were held together with handmade wood needles. The documents were created in the local language, Likeleve, and French. Included are Weiss' translations into French of these documents.
The records contain additional Kwilu administration documents, generally government documents, correspondence, and reports, arranged chronologically in two groups, general documents and specific subject related documents.
Additional translations into French, summaries, and indexes of the original Kwilu Rebellion documents and some Kwilu Administration documents, created by Weiss are also available. Additional materials included were given to Weiss by Professor Benoit Verhaegen, another noted academic working on aspects of the Kwilu Rebellion.
Bundundu Government documents were collected by Weiss in 1972 with the backing of the State/Party, the MPR, for use in a more general analysis of the Province than the focused Kwilu Documents. The documents from various levels of the administration (colonial and post-colonial) focused on the province (Leopoldville Province until shortly after independence and later variously Kwilu Province and Bandundu Province) where the Kwilu Rebellion occurred.
Sound recordings include interviews with individuals involved in the Kwilu Rebellion, Constant N'dom, Felix Mukulubundu, and W. Mwatha. Constant N'dom, a high-school student when the Kwilu Rebellion broke out, was recruited and assigned to the Direction Générale, the highest administrative organ of the rebellion. After the rebellion, he married and moved to Belgium, later returning. In 2006 elections, he joined the opposition to J. Kabila and was elected member of Parliament from the Kwilu region. The late Felix Mukulubundu came from the Kwilu, where he actively participated in the CNL. He was assigned to head a training camp for Congo partisans located not far from Brazzaville, a project that was rapidly abandoned. Thus, Mukulubundu never actively participated in the rebellion in the Congo.
Arrangement
The collection has generally been kept in the original order of the creator.
Weiss, Herbert F.; Congo (Democratic Republic)--History.; Kwilu region (Congo)--History.
- Microfilm Reel Content Guide
  Downloadable PDF file of the Microfilm Reel Content Guide
- Kwilu Rebellion documents, in numbered sequence, 1964.
  Scope and Contents note
  Documents about the Kwilu rebellion, abandoned by a section of the Rebellion's general headquarters unit. Includes translations in French of selected documents. In numbered sequence, although not all numbers are present in the documents
  - "Les partisans au Kwilu: Analyse des origins sociales des membres et cadres des équipes de base" and "Kwilu Rebellion Documents", by Herbert Weiss, undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - 1-0688, 0790-1000 (Folder 1: 2-11)
  - 1001-1618, 2000-2645 (Box-folder 2: 1-12)
  - 3000-4000 (Box-folder 3: 1-10)
  - 4001-4685, 4700-5000 (Box-folder 4: 1-9)
  - 5000-5796 (Box-folder 5: 1-9)
  - Kwilu Rebel équipe Lists, circa 1960. (Box-folder 6: 1)
    Missing numbers from previous files may be found here. File includes various numbers from 0183-5647.
  - Translations into French, documents 0001-2296 (Folder 6: 2-7)
  - Translations into French, documents 2301-5682 (Box-folder 7: 1-12)
- Kwilu Administration documents, 1959-1966.
  Generally government documents, correspondence, and reports. Arranged chronologically in two groups, general documents and specific subject related documents. Some materials are numbered and correspond to the card files below
  - undated, 1959-1966 (Folder 7: 13)
  - 1960-1963 (Folder 7: 14)
  - 1964 (Folder 7: 15)
  - 1965-1966. (Box-folder 8: 1)
    Numbered 6001-6085
  - 1965-1972. (Folder 8: 2-5)
    Numbered G65-G72
  - Photocopied documents, government documents regarding rebellion, 1964. (Folder 8: 6-10)
    Numbered B97-B256
  - Kwilu Idiofa (territory) administrative reports, 1960-1961 (Folder 8: 11-12)
  - Rebellion, 1960-1964 (Folder 8: 13-14)
  - Early rebellion, 1963 (Box-folder 9: 1-2)
  - David J. Yongo, 1963-1966. (Folder 9: 3)
    Numbered Q1-Q33
  - Rebellion, 1964-1965 (Folder 9: 4-5)
  - Administration and Church, 1964-1966 (Folder 9: 6-7)
- Indexes and Card files, undated, 1979.
  Summary abstracts on cards of both the Kwilu Rebellion Documents and some Kwilu Administration Documents created by Herbert Weiss. Also includes an unused attempt to categorize the content of the documents by computer program reports. Arranged in numerical sequence, although not all numbers are present in the documents
  - Indexes and Computer Reports, undated (Folder 9: 8-9)
    Weiss' attempt to categorize the content of the documents by computer program reports, and other miscellany, eventually unused.
  - Data tape, 1979 (Tape cabinet Tape cabinet)
  - Card files, undated
    - 1-2100 (Folder 9: 10)
    - 2101-4000 (Folder 9: 11)
    - 4001-5500 (Folder 9: 12)
    - 5501-5796 (Folder 9: 13)
    - 6001-6085 (Folder 9: 13)
    - ADM IA 1 - IA 23 (Folder 9: 13)
    - ADM B1-B256 (Folder 9: 13)
    - ADM Q1-Q32 (Folder 9: 13)
- Professor Benoit Verhaegen Kwilu materials, circa 1962-1966.
  Sources, interviews and miscellany collected from Verhaegen, author of Rébellions au Congo, Vol 1 & 2 (CRISP, Brussels, 1969). Arranged by physical form
  - Kwilu Administration sources, circa 1962-1966 (Box-folder 9: 10-11)
  - Interviews and miscellany (Folder 9: 12)
- Bandundu Province Government Documents, 1956-1959.
  Documents from various levels of the Administration (colonial and post-colonial) focused on the province (Leopoldville Province until shortly after independence and later variously Kwilu Province and Bandundu Province) where the Kwilu Rebellion occurred.
  - 1956-1959 (Box-folder 13: 1)
  - 1961-1962 (Folder 13: 2-3)
  - 1965-1966 (Folder 13: 4-5)
  - 1965-1966 (Box-folder 14: 1-2)
  - 1966 (Folder 14: 3-4)
  - 1967-1968 (Folder 14: 5-6)
  - 1969 (Folder 14: 7-8)
  - 1970 (Folder 14: 9-10)
  - 1971 (Folder 14: 11-12)
  - 1972 (Folder 14: 13)
- Sound Recordings, 1975 1980-1988
  Interviews of Constant N'dom, assigned to the Direction Générale, the highest administrative organ of the rebellion, and Felix Mukulubundu, who actively participated in the CNL and was assigned to head a training camp for Congo partisans. Arranged alphabetically by interviewee, then chronologically with notations from original labels.
  - Interviews of Constant N'dom, 1975, 1988 (Box 15)
    - Weiss N'Dom, undated
      Conditions Governing Access note
      Use copy reference number: 76079_a_0000925
    - N'Dom, 1975 July 5
      Use copy reference number: 76079_a_0000924
      Program on side A seems to be recorded over a recording of a lesson on "The Changing Nature of American Politics". Applicable program on this side lasts about twenty minutes. Side B is dictation for letters on culture. In English.
    - Comments on "F", Doc Ser. A, 1988 July; 2.0 cassettes
      Use copy reference number: 76079_a_0000927
    - N'Dom Weiss Tape 3, 1988 July 26
    - N'Dom Doc G, 1988 October
      Use copy reference number: 76079_a_0000928
    - N'Dom "Conflicts" 7/18/89, 1989 July 18
      Use copy reference number: 76079_a_0000929
    - N'Dom 7/25/89, DG replies continued
      Use copy reference number: 76079_a_0000931
    - N'Dom, 1989 July 20 and 1989 July 24
      Use copy reference number: 76079_a_0000930
    - N'Dom July 28, 89, DG, N'Dom DG docs. 7/31/89
      Use copy reference number: 76079_a_0000932
    - N'Dom/Weiss discussion for September 1989
      Use copy reference number: 76079_a_0000933
  - Interviews of Felix Mukulubundu, 1984 (Box 15)
    - Mukulu. Kw. Reb and ABO Mukulubundu, Mmme Mulele +, Mukulubundu, 1984 April 5
      Use copy reference number: 76079_a_0000922
    - Mukulubundu, 1984 December 17-18
      Use copy reference number: 76079_a_0000921
      (4 cassettes, recorded on both sides) Taped interview with Felix Mukulubundu in French.
  - Interview W. Mwatha BX 6/30/75, Warren Weinstein Human rights 12/80, 1975 June 30, 1980 December. (Box 15)
    Use copy reference number: 76079_a_0000923
    Side A: Interview with Mwatha; Side B: Warren Weinstein, human rights. Weinstein discusses human rights in Africa during the Nixon and Carter administrations. The Mwatha interview is in French, the Weinstein interview is in English.
- Kwilu Rebellion documents II, 1955-1970 (Folder 16-17)
  - Kwilu rebellion equipé and village lists, 1964 (Folder 16: 1-7)
    Documents were a part of the Kwilu Rebellion documents, in numbered sequence, separated for research use by Herbert Weiss.
  - Kwilu Rebellion demography 1961-1969 chart, undated (Folder 16: 8)
  - Kwilu Rebellion documents, missionary materials retained by the rebels, circa 1955. (Folder 16: 9)
    The documents are a part of the foot locker of rebel documents acquired by Herbert Weiss that created the Kwilu Rebellion documents series.
  - Kwilu rebellion documents French translations, numbered over 6000, 1964-1966 (Folder 16: 10)
  - Non-rebel Kwilu documents, 1966 (Folder 16: 11)
  - Idiofa territory original administrative documents, 1955-1970 (Folder 16: 12-14)
  - Gungu (Kondu) administrative documents, 1960-1970 (Folder 16: 15-20)
  - Gungu (Kondu) administrative documents, 1960-1970 (Folder 17: 1-6)
- Kwilu Administration documents II, 1959-1978. (Folder 17-18)
  Mainly Photocopies.
  - Kwilu pre-independence administrative documents, 1959-1960. (Folder 17: 7)
    Includes original documents
  - Kwilu Province administrative documents (Folder 17)
    - 1961-1962 (Folder 17: 8)
    - 1962 (Folder 17: 9-11)
    - 1963 (Folder 17: 12-16)
    - 1964 (Folder 17: 17)
    - 1964 (Folder 18: 1-2)
    - 1966 (Folder 18: 3-10)
  - Kikwit, Kwilu, administrative documents, 1963 (Folder 18: 11-12)
  - Kwilu appeal, 1965 (Folder 18: 13)
  - Kwilu post-rebellion development, 1966 (Folder 18: 14)
- Bandundu Administration documents II, 1964-1978. (Folder 18-19)
  Photocopies.
  - Bandundu Province administrative documents (Folder 18:)
    - 1964-1965 (Folder 18: 15-16)
    - 1965 (Folder 18: 17-19)
    - 1965 (Folder 19: 1-5)
  - Idiofa Uprising, Bandundu, Kwilu, 1978 (Folder 19: 6)
- Interview files, circa 1972-1984 (Folder 19)
  - Interview Questionnaires of former rebels, N'Dom research, circa 1972 (Folder 19: 7)
  - Ludo interviews, 1978 (Folder 19: 8)
  - Mukulubundu (early Kwilu rebel leader), undated (Folder 19: 9)
  - Mukulubundu interview transcript, 1984 (Folder 19: 10)
- Research materials, 1933-1988 (Folder 20)
  - Les Bayansi du Bas Kwilu, by R. de Beaucorps, 1933 (Folder 20: 1)
  - Principes fondamentaux d'une révolution, handwritten document, undated (Folder 20: 2)
  - Kwilu periodicals, 1966 (Folder 20: 3)
  - Failed attempts to quantify information in Kwilu Rebellion documents with computers at MIT, circa 1968-1970 (Folder 20: 4-5)
  - Kwilu Rebellion published participant and expert commentaries, circa 1988 (Folder 20: 6)